What’s the best way
to stay healthy
in the face of so much
conflicting nutrition information?
Well, ideally, you would
go to the source.
The gold standard;
the peer-reviewed
medical literature.
Read through stacks of
the latest medical journals.
But who’s got
time for that?
I do!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we hope to settle
the debate once and for all
of the role of cholesterol
in heart disease.
The cholesterol controversy is over.
In fact, you can argue
it was over a century ago.
It seemed obvious in 1920 that
high cholesterol levels in the blood
infiltrating your artery walls was
the cause of coronary heart disease,
the #1 killer of men and women,
confirmed as unequivocally
as the revelation that blood
circulated throughout the body
or that the tuberculosis
bacteria causes tuberculosis.
The question is why
did it take so long?
What is so puzzling is why
we have to work so hard
to sell the message
given what seems to be
an unbeatable amount
of hard evidence.
Many rejected the cholesterol-
heart disease link because
so many patients were
dying of coronary heart disease
despite so-called perfectly
normal cholesterol levels.
Of course as I've detailed before,
having normal cholesterol levels
in a society where it's normal
to drop dead of a heart attack
isn't exactly saying much.
Ideally, we want to get our total
cholesterol well under 150,
since having high cholesterol
levels in your blood
is thought of as the only direct
atherosclerotic risk factor.
All the other things -- smoking,
high blood pressure, diabetes,
inactivity, obesity --
just exacerbate the damage
caused by the high cholesterol.
Another factor may be the
preoccupation of cardiologists
with all the new fancy gadgets
and procedures out there.
It's like we train them
to be highly-skilled,
high-tech fighter pilots
to fight a war,
but then sent them on some boring
preventive diplomatic mission.
But the reasons may be
even more personal than that.
As an editorial in the Journal of
the American Heart Association
asked nearly 50 years ago,
why do we pretend the cause
of heart disease is mysterious?
There is no mystery as to why
the incidence of heart disease,
like that of lung disease
and of venereal disease --
sexually-transmitted disease --
continues to rise for many decades
after the cause is established.
Why?
Because human beings,
including physicians,
are eager for excuses,
not to face annoying facts,
and so they continue to do things
which are agreeable but hazardous.
People tend to reject new ideas,
even when they don't impose
any change in our way of life,
and it's almost impossible
for most men to accept any
suggestion that it might be wise
to give up agreeable habits
such as smoking, unsafe sex,
or eating their favorite foods.
This continuing challenge is
represented by a senior professor
of medicine who questioned whether
an alteration of diet would really
affect the course of heart disease.
These professors know the facts.
The problem is that they,
like so many patients,
will not allow themselves
to believe the message.
Eating rich food just means
too much to too many people,
even when it's our
gravest mortal threat.
Scientific consensus panels going
back decades established
beyond a reasonable doubt
that lowering LDL cholesterol
reduces the risk of heart attacks.
Consistent evidence
unequivocally establishes that LDL
causes our #1 killer, atherosclerotic
cardiovascular disease.
And what raises LDL cholesterol?
Saturated fat.
And where is cholesterol-raising
saturated fat found?
The #1 source is dairy,
the #2 source is chicken,
then pastries, pork, and burgers.
And it's not just saturated fat.
Dietary cholesterol has been known
as a dominant factor in the genesis
of atherosclerosis since 1908,
which is why we should lower
our intake of saturated fats,
trans fats and dietary cholesterol
as much as possible.
This is consistent with
how our biology evolved.
Extensive evidence clearly
indicates that a plant-based diet
was the traditional eating pattern
of our distant ancestors,
and so dietary cholesterol intakes
were typically very low,
while at the same time we were
packing in whole plant foods
containing components like fiber
to help us eliminate cholesterol.
Where is dietary cholesterol
coming from now?
Overwhelmingly eggs,
with the #2 source chicken,
then beef, dairy, and pork.
So wait a second.
If the Institute of Medicine
recommends that individuals
consume as little dietary
cholesterol as possible,
presumably that would mean
cutting out foods like eggs entirely.
But does eating cholesterol actually
raise your blood cholesterol?
We'll find out next.
The question, does egg feeding
(in other words, dietary cholesterol)
affect the level of cholesterol in the
blood, was answered 40 years ago.
Give someone half a cup of eggs
a day and within 2, 3, 4 weeks
their cholesterol keeps going up,
and then stop the eggs
by switching to an egg substitute
and the cholesterol comes down.
Or start people on the egg
substitute and not much happens,
but then start feeding eggs and
their cholesterol shoots right up.
Put people on a cholesterol-free
diet and their cholesterols drop.
But then add some
egg yolk cholesterol and
their cholesterol goes up.
Take it away and their
cholesterol goes down.
You could do this all year.
And it's within days:
10 days of eggs and
cholesterol shot up 50 points.
Take the eggs away
and it comes back down.
You can reproduce this effect
over and over and over and over,
though evidently penguin omelets
are only about half as deadly.
Switch people from
a high cholesterol diet
to a cholesterol free diet,
and you can drop
blood cholesterol levels
as much as a hundred points.
OK, but that was giving people more
than a half cup of egg yolks a day.
But even just a single egg a day can
increase people's LDL cholesterol 12%.
Put all the studies together
in this 2020 meta-analysis,
more than 50 randomized
controlled trials feeding people eggs,
and egg consumption significantly
increases LDL-cholesterol, period.
Now studies funded by the Egg
Board use a variety of methods
to try to minimize the reported
negative health effects of eggs
by, for example, claiming that
dietary cholesterol affects
only certain people.
That's actually been put to the
test, and only 3% were even
potentially "nonresponders"
to dietary cholesterol,
and even these probably evidenced
some adverse response.
Wait, then how was the Egg Board
able to design a study in which
egg intake did not change
blood cholesterol?
By feeding them sufficiently
large quantities of dairy and meat.
See, there's a plateau effect.
Though all lines of evidence converge
to indicate that dietary cholesterol
is a major factor in promoting
hardening of the arteries,
confusion about dietary
cholesterol has arisen because
above a certain ceiling you basically
max out cholesterol absorption.
Check it out. If you're eating
a strictly plant-based diet
with a baseline of zero cholesterol
intake, and you start adding meat,
dairy or eggs to your diet,
you can get a dramatic
rise in blood cholesterol.
But as your diet starts out more
and more meaty, you can saturate
your system and basically max
out on the additional effect.
So no wonder the Egg Board
packed in the extra meat and dairy
to mask the egg effect.
A systematic review of egg industry
"Funding and Cholesterol Research "
sought out to see if industry-funded
studies were more likely to report
conclusions that were not supported
by their own objective findings.
Of the non industry-funded studies
on the effect of egg ingestion on
cholesterol, cholesterol increases
were reported in about 90%.
Among industry-funded studies,
cholesterol increases were
reported in about 90%.
In other words, even the egg
industry funded studies showed
eggs increased blood cholesterol,
and not a single study
funded by anyone
showed a significant decrease.
Okay, but here's the crazy part.
About half of the industry-funded
studies reported conclusions
that were discordant
with their own results.
In other words, they found
that cholesterol went up,
but if you read their conclusions,
they exonerated eggs.
That's why you can't
just read the abstract.
You actually have to
see what they found.
Readers, editors, and the
public should remain alert
to funding sources in interpreting
study findings and conclusions.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.